Kappa Delta Sorority; Records ua800.006
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Kappa Delta Sorority Records
1899-2001, Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua800.006
7.1 cubic ft.
The Kappa Delta Sorority Records contain documents related to the formation, activities and alumnae of the Kappa Delta Sorority at the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Kappa Delta Records were originally transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives from the Alumni Association in 1989. Since then the collection has been augmented several times through donations from individual alumni.
Biographical Sketch
The Kappa Delta Sorority is the successor to the Kappa Delta Society, founded at the New York State Normal College (now the University at Albany) on June 16, 1897. The Kappa Delta Society's purpose was to "promote social and literary advancement." Although inquiries into nationalization were made between 1919 and 1922, the Albany Kappa Delta was not a part of the national organization of the same name.
The constitution of the Kappa Delta Society stated that the object of the Society was "the attainment toward culture among its members." By 1930 the sorority's goal changed to the more contemporary "promotion of fellowship among its members."
Kappa Delta was incorporated in Albany in April 1922. The purpose of the Kappa Delta Corporation was to "promote fraternal, intellectual, and social pursuits among its members and to oversee the sale and upkeep of any property it may own." The corporation subsequently purchased a sorority house at 380 Western Avenue, which was occupied by the sorority until it was sold to the College of St. Rose in the 1960s.
Kappa Delta maintained certain traditions at various times in its history. Some traditions were eventually phased out, such as the purchasing of an engraved silver spoon for each baby born to a sister within five years of her graduation. Others, like the formal events held each fall and spring, stood the test of time even as they evolved and changed. And still others, like the annual alumnae luncheon, faded away only to be revived in later years.
Kappa Delta was dissolved in the late fall of 1979 or the early spring of 1980, because of limited interest in sororities on campus at that time. The Corporation continued after the folding of the active sorority as the financial vehicle for administering Kappa Delta funds, to be used for alumnae meetings and scholarships.
Scope and Contents
The Kappa Delta Sorority Records include administrative files, subject files, alumnae newsletters, photographs, scrapbooks, and memorabilia objects. The administrative and subject files contain meeting minutes, constitutions and by-laws, membership and initiation lists, and other records relating to the functioning of the sorority, as well as materials related to traditions and sorority events. The Alumni Association newsletters date from the 1970s and 1980s, and include information about the active chapter of Kappa Delta, sorority alumnae updates and events, and the business concerns of the Kappa Delta Corporation. There are both candid photographs and official posed portraits. The collection contains several complete scrapbooks as well as folders with loose items removed from scrapbooks. The memorabilia items include shirts, blankets, jewelry, and other objects.
Separated Materials
Additional material related to the Kappa Delta Sorority can be found in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in the Alumni Memorabilia Collection, Classes of 1921, 1923, 1931, 1939, 1940, 1944, 1946, and 1959; and the University Archives Photograph Collection. The University at Albany Alumni House holds a framed Kappa Delta sheepskin as well as the six-piece Kappa Delta sterling silver tea service.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Administrative and Subject Files, 1899-2001, Undated
Series 2 - Alumni Association Newsletters, 1973-1985
Series 3 - Scrapbooks and Photographs, 1937-1997, Undated
Series 4 - Memorabilia, 1963-1997, Undated
All series are arranged chronologically.
Literature; Greek letter societies--New York (State)--Albany; Sorority songs; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Women--New York (State)--Albany--Societies and clubs; Albany (N.Y.); Correspondence; Photographs; Programs (documents); Scrapbooks; UAlbany Student Groups; Minutes (administrative records); State University of New York at Albany; Kappa Delta Sorority
- Administrative and Subject Files, 1899-2001; Undated; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records relating to the administration and activities of the Kappa Delta Sorority. Meeting minutes, membership and initiation lists, constitutions and by-laws, and other materials document the sorority's functioning from shortly after its founding, in 1899, to 1978. There are no minutes for 1903-1923, 1933-1934, 1941-1950, or 1975-1980. This series also includes sorority traditions, publicity materials, and some materials relating to alumnae.
  - Minutes, 1899-1902 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - History from The Neon, 1900 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Nationalization correspondence, 1919-1922 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1924-1928 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1928-1932 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Constitution and membership lists, 1930-1950 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1935-1940 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Certificates of indebtedness, 1941; 1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Initiation lists, 1950-1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1954-1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1956-1958 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1958-1960 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Traditions and transcription, 1959; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Resolutions, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Membership lists, 1962; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Financial statement, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Pledge list, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 1964-1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Meeting notes, 1967-1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clippings, ca. 1968 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Evaluations, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Meeting notes, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Family trees, ca. 1968-1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Family trees, ca. 1968-1977 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - By-law revisions, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - Program for Holiday Sing, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - Minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 34)
  - Scholarship announcement and applications, 1972; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 35)
  - Event publicity, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 36)
  - Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 37)
  - Event publicity, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 38)
  - Rush materials, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 39)
  - Event publicity, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 40)
  - Minutes, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 41)
  - Event publicity, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 42)
  - Event publicity, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 43)
  - Alumni memories from Centennial celebration, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 44)
  - Centennial celebration, 1997 (Video-tape 1)
  - Centennial program and newsletter, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 45)
  - Career histories of the women of Kappa Delta, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 46)
  - Albany State and Kappa Deltas in the Class of 1941, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 47)
  - Kappa Delta Mother Goose Nursery Rhyme book, Undated (Flat-file 1)
  - Letterhead and oath, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 48)
  - Songs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 49)
- Alumni Association Newsletter, 1973-1985; 2
  This series consists of newsletters mailed out to Kappa Delta alumnae, dated 1973-1974, 1976, and 1979-1985. The newsletters include news from the active chapter, career and life updates from alumni, planning for alumni events, and information about the financial dealings of the Kappa Delta Corporation.
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1973 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 50)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 51)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 52)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1979 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 53)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1980 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 54)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1981 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 55)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1983 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 56)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1984 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 57)
  - Alumni Association newsletter, 1985 (Box 1 (2-Alumni Association Newsletter), Folder 58)
- Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1937-1997; Undated; 3
  This series includes several years' worth of formal posed portraits and composites of the whole sorority, as well as candids contributed from individuals. There are several complete scrapbooks, both the "official" scrapbooks kept by the sorority historians each year and personal scrapbooks from sorority members. This series also includes several folders containing loose materials initially housed within scrapbooks, such as photographs, programs, invitations and other keepsakes.
  - Loose photographs and newspaper clippings from scrapbook, 1937-1940 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 59)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 1939-1944 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 60)
  - Loose scrapbook items, 1943-1946 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 61)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 1954-1957 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 62-63)
  - 11x14 Composites, 1955; 1957 (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 1956-1957 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 64)
  - Photographs, 1956-1957 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 65)
  - 28.5x36.75 Composite, 1959-1960 (Flat-file 2)
  - Photographs, 1959; Undated (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 66)
  - 25x30 Composite, 1960-1961 (Flat-file 2)
  - Kappa Delta scrapbook, 1960-1961 (Oversized 2)
  - 25x30 Composite, 1961-1962 (Flat-file 2)
  - 28x36 Composite, 1962-1963 (Flat-file 2)
  - 23x26 Composite, 1963-1964 (Flat-file 3)
  - 32x40 Composite, 1964-1965 (Flat-file 3)
  - Loose scrapbook items, 1964-1965; Undated (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 67)
  - 28x36 Composite, 1965-1966 (Flat-file 3)
  - 30x37 Composite, 1966-1967 (Flat-file 4)
  - Kappa Delta scrapbook, 1966-1967 (Oversized 3)
  - 28.5x36.75 Composite, 1967-1968 (Flat-file 4)
  - Photographs, ca. 1968 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 68)
  - Photographs from family trees, ca. 1968 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 69)
  - 30x37 Composite, 1968-1969 (Flat-file 4)
  - Kappa Delta Scrapbook, 1968-1969 (Oversized 4)
  - 28x36 Composite, 1969-1970 (Flat-file 4)
  - Kappa Delta scrapbook, 1969-1970 (Oversized 5)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 70)
  - 32x40 Composite, 1970-1971 (Flat-file 4)
  - Kappa Delta scrapbook, 1970-1971 (Oversized 6)
  - Personal scrapbook, 1970-1972 (Oversized 7)
  - 14x20 group portrait by David Slawsky, 1973 (Oversized 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 71)
  - Photograph, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 72)
  - 14x20 group portrait, ca. 1974 (Oversized 1, Folder 4)
  - 25x30 Composite, 1974-1975 (Flat-file 5)
  - Photographs, 1974; 1976 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 73)
  - 25x30 Composite, 1975-1976 (Flat-file 5)
  - 11x14 composites, 1975; 1975-1976; 1976-1977 (Oversized 1, Folder 5)
  - 25x30 Composite, 1976-1977 (Flat-file 5)
  - Photographs and negatives, 1979; Undated (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 74)
  - Photograph, ca. 1979 (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 75)
  - Photo album of Centennial celebration, 1997 (Oversized 8)
  - Photograph of sorority house on Western Ave, Undated (Box 1 (3-Photographs and Scrapbooks), Folder 76)
- Memorabilia, 1963-1997; Undated; 4
  The Memorabilia series includes objects related to Kappa Delta. There are textiles such as shirts and blankets; jewelry; glassware and mugs; plaques; and other objects either used by the sorority or bearing the Kappa Delta symbol.
  - Beer stein, Spring Weekend favor, ca. 1963 (Artifact-box 1)
  - Spring weekend blanket, 1965 (Artifact-box 2)
  - Spring Weekend wooden goblet, 1966 (Artifact-box 3)
  - Albany State beer mugs, 1967 (Artifact-box 4)
  - Paddles, 1972; 1975 (Artifact-box 3)
  - Plaque for contributions to Alumni House, 1974 (Artifact-box 3)
  - Plaque for outstanding community support, 1976 (Artifact-box 3)
  - Candle from Centennial celebration, 1997 (Artifact-box 5)
  - Banner, Undated (Artifact-box 2)
  - Blazer, Undated (Artifact-box 2)
  - Scarf, Undated (Artifact-box 2)
  - Candle snuffer, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta brooch, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta jewelry box, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta necklace, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta necklace, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta pin, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta pin and University at Albany pin, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Kappa Delta pin belonging to Laura Bristol Chapman '13, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Two Kappa Delta pins, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - "Smile on your brother" button, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Wooden gavel, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Blanket, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Embroidered pillow, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Leather Kappa Delta pillowcase, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Two sweatshirts, Undated (Artifact-box 7)
  - "Vinnies" t-shirt, Undated (Artifact-box 7)
  - Metal platter, Undated (Artifact-box 8)
  - Kappa Delta lightbox sign, Undated (Oversized 9)